<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Greg Macfarlane</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Greg Macfarlane</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Can Utah County Choose to Grow Sustainably?</title>
      <link>/post/sustainable_utahco/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2020 13:42:54 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/sustainable_utahco/</guid>
      <description>Last week the Deseret News ran a contributed opinion piece by Andrew Skabelund1 in which he argued that the rapid development of Silicon Slopes in north Utah County comes at the cost of Utah County&amp;rsquo;s value as agricultural land. He cites an interesting fact (originally credited to Jared Farmer) I had not known previously:
 the Native Americans living in Utah Valley did not see the mountains as the primary feature of the landscape; instead, their perspective was dominated by Utah Lake and the Provo River, which &amp;mdash; though hard to believe now &amp;mdash; were abundant sources of food.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transit Safety</title>
      <link>/post/safety/transit-safety/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/safety/transit-safety/</guid>
      <description>I came across this graphic from an APTA Factbook(p. 20) which shows transit with an enormous safety advantage over automobiles. I was curious if I could update the data using information from the Bureau of Transportation Statistics.
knitr::include_graphics(&amp;quot;https://i.imgur.com/7txj1aA.png&amp;quot;) Passenger Miles First, we want to get passenger miles traveled by different modes. The BTS has this data in an Excel spreadsheet at https://www.bts.gov/content/us-passenger-miles. The data in the spreadsheet is somewhat spotty, and there are plenty of footnotes describing the fact that the sources of the different elements have changed over the years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Autonomous Vehicles with Passive Data</title>
      <link>/post/passiveavs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/passiveavs/</guid>
      <description>Last summer I did some work with my friend and colleague Josie Kressner applying our data-driven model to potential AV scenarios. I wrote this up over at the Transport Foundry blog in a series of three posts:
 Modeling autonomous vehicles with passive data Modeling shared autonomous vehicles Modeling private autonomous vehicles  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Urban Church</title>
      <link>/post/urbanchurch/urban-temples/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/urbanchurch/urban-temples/</guid>
      <description>Last night I read the surprising announcement that the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints is financing the development and construction of a 32 floor residential and commercial building in the heart of downtown Philadelphia. The Church has owned this property for a while, and has already begun construction on the adjacent Philadelphia Temple, to be opened in 2016.
The Church is no stranger to urban development. A central doctrine of early Mormonism was the idea of Zion, a city where the faithful would gather to prepare the world for the return of Christ.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mechanisms of Decentralization</title>
      <link>/post/decentralization/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/decentralization/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: This essay was originally written for Brian Stone&amp;rsquo;s graduate Land Use and Transportation Course.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;The true center of the new [suburb] is not in some downtown business district but in each residential unit. - Robert Fishman&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The typical city in the United States in the early part of the twenty-first
century has a radically different urban form compared to its urban predecessors
at the turn of the nineteenth or even the twentieth. Fishman, in the quote above
this essay, argues that the modern city has completely disintegrated into the
homes of its residents in an extreme polycentrism that is fundamentally
different from what existed before. There was once a true center, in “some
downtown business district,” and now there is not; each family or domestic unit
has turned themselves inward towards their own lives and home rather than
engaging with society around a particular core. This perspective is certainly
valid, but is nonetheless urban-centric. There is a parallel perspective – if
not necessarily a competing one – that the “true center” was never in that
business district to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back to the Future</title>
      <link>/post/back-to-the-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/back-to-the-future/</guid>
      <description>In the classic Robert Zemeckis movie Back to the Future, Marty McFly explains to Doc Brown that the Delorean/time machine he (Doc) invented is nuclear-powered,1 and that the only obstacle to sending Marty back to the future (1985) is obtaining some plutonium. I love Doc&amp;rsquo;s response:
 I&amp;rsquo;m sure that in 1985, plutonium is available in every corner drugstore, but in 1955, it&amp;rsquo;s a little hard to come by.
 The irony in this statement of course being that in spite of sweeping changes to fashions, music, politics – and Marty&amp;rsquo;s own mother – plutonium is still mercifully difficult to obtain, and the future Doc Brown had to contract with Libyan terrorists to get some.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>